南极洲
Antarctica.
地球上极其寒冷、恶劣和偏远的一片大陆。
The coldest, the harshest and the
most remote continent on Earth.
前人尚未下潜到其周边的深海。
No human being has ever descended
into the depths that surround it...
我们这是首次。
until now.
探索深海的难度,
堪比探索太空。
The deep ocean is as challenging to
explore as space.
人类对海洋深处的了解
We know more about the surface of
Mars than we do about the
还不如对火星表面的了解多。
deepest parts of our seas.
现在我们终于有能力
深潜到这些无人涉足的地方
Now we can dive these uncharted
depths to discover
去发掘其隐藏的奥妙。
what secrets lie beneath.
沿着水下的冰山峭壁下潜，
Sinking down beside the submerged
wall of an iceberg,
我们进入了一个冷酷无情的世界。
we enter an unforgiving world.
这些水域在地球上最为冰冷。
These waters are
the coldest on Earth.
随着我们下潜，水压持续增强。
As we descend into the deep, the
pressure increases relentlessly.
光线尽无，漆黑一片。
And the light from above
all but disappears.
然而，非常神奇……
Yet, incredibly...
这里有生物。
there is life here.
我们原以为，
极地海洋之深深处，
We might have expected that, deep
beneath the surface of
应是一片不毛之地。
the polar seas, the waters would be
truly barren.
然而，这里的生物
却丰富得无法想像。
But in fact we find life here in
unimaginable abundance.
这种丰富也并非局限于南极水域。
Nor is such great abundance confined
to Antarctic waters.
洋流使地球上
几乎所有海洋的深深处
Currents carry this richness into
the depths of almost every ocean
都这么丰富。
around the world.
很吃惊吧，在深海处，
Astonishingly, in the deep sea,
生命竟比地球其他地方都要丰富
there is more life than anywhere else on Earth.
第二集
洋深深处
倾情翻译：高智衡（Q:11279470)
特别鸣谢：岚岚小朋友。You are the motivation.
仅供学习 20171109
光照衰减，海里越来越黑。
The sunlight fades
and the seas darken.
在太平洋海面200米下，
Here in the Pacific,
200 metres down,
恍如进入了外星世界。
we enter an alien world.
这里是阴阳魔界——
（注：学名中层区，海面下200--1000米处）
The Twilight Zone -
一个恒久幽暗的海域。
a sea of eternal gloom.
充斥着奇妙的生物。
There are strange creatures here.
火体虫
A pyrosome.
啫哩状的体型长达2米，
A tube of jelly two metres long that
dwarfs a visitor from above --
令海上游下来的这只海洋白鳍鲨
也相形见绌了。
an oceanic whitetip shark.
仅有微弱光线能抵达这里。
Only a tiny amount of light filters
down this far.
所以这里的生物
必须充分利用每一线余辉。
Survival here means making the most
of every last glimmer.
剑鱼（又名箭鱼）
A swordfish.
其眼球大如网球，
Its eyes are as big as tennis balls,
哪怕光线再暗，它也能看得见。
to help it see
in the perpetual dusk.
乌贼，
A squid,
这个品种，仅此独有。
but this is one
that lives only here.
它的右眼总是看着下方。
Its right eye looks
permanently downwards.
而左眼大得多，并且总是盯着上方，
But its left eye is much bigger and
trained upwards to detect the
搜寻着在上面猎物的身影。
silhouettes of prey
swimming nearer the surface.
它的别名叫“斗鸡眼乌贼”，很贴切吧。
No wonder it's nicknamed
"the cockeyed squid".
更为神妙的。
And even stranger.
这叫桶眼鱼……
This is barreleye...
它的头部全透明，
a fish with a transparent head
里面全是胶状物，
所以它可透过脑袋望向头顶。
filled with jelly so that it can
look up through its skull.
目前所知，这个阴阳魔界，
We now know that the Twilight Zone
is a refuge for an incredible
为海洋里多达90%的鱼类提供了庇护所。
90% of all fish in the ocean.
夜晚，大量灯笼鱼群迁徙到海面，
Only at night do vast shoals of
lanternfish migrate to the surface
捕食微细的浮游生物。
to feed on tiny plankton.
白天，它们躲回下面这里。
By day, they retreat back down here.
洪堡鱿鱼
Humboldt squid.
长达2米，重50公斤。
Two metres long
and 50 kilos in weight.
如大多数鱿鱼一样，他们是贪婪猎手。
Like most squid,
they're voracious hunters.
这里有数百只。
There are hundreds of them.
它们发现了灯笼鱼群，
They've found a shoal
of lanternfish,
就躲在这南非海岸外800米的海底处。
hiding 800 metres down,
off the coast of South America.
触须上布满了有力的吸盘，
Their tentacles are armed with
powerful suckers
捕捉猎物简直是手到拿来。
with which they grab their prey.
当没有灯笼鱼后……
And when there are no more
lanternfish to be found...
它们竟自相残杀。
they turn on each other.
这只鱿鱼触须内捉了只小鱿鱼。
This squid has caught a smaller one
in its tentacles.
为了隐藏猎物，
To hide its capture from the rest,
它喷出了墨汁。
it releases a smokescreen
of black ink.
但这时另一只更大的鱿鱼过来抢食……
But then an even bigger one
challenges it...
猎物被抢走了。
and steals its catch.
阴阳魔界是洪堡鱿鱼捕猎的最爱场所。
The Twilight Zone is the Humboldt
squid's favoured hunting ground.
他们不会再下潜了……
They seldom go deeper...
再往下，就是暗无天日的黑暗世界……
into the world of perpetual
blackness below...
这里叫午夜魔界。
（注：学名半深海区，海面下1000-4000米处）
The Midnight Zone.
这里深达一千米，阳光已无力抵达。
Two thirds of a mile from the
surface, beyond the reach the sun.
这是个巨大、黑暗而空旷的场所，
A giant black void,
大到比地球上所有其他栖息地加起来都大。
larger than all the rest of the
world's habitats combined.
这里也有生命……
There's life here...
超越我们所知。
but not as we know it.
形如外星物种的生物
发出眩目的光辉。
Alien-like creatures produce
dazzling displays of light.
几乎所有动物都要吸引异性和警吓敌人。
Nearly all animals need to attract
mates and repel predators.
光线式表达广泛使用，
This language of light is so
widespread here that these signals
所以光信号也许是地球上
are probably the commonest
form of communication
最常见的沟通形式了。
on the entire planet.
然而我们知之甚少。
And yet we still know
little about them.
打猎者为自己打灯，
Hunters illuminate themselves,
and by doing so
同时也吸引那些好奇心重的猎物。
attract inquisitive prey.
尖牙鱼。
This is fangtooth.
类似体型的鱼类中，它的牙齿是最大的。
It has the largest teeth for its
size of any fish.
其头部和身体布满了压力感应器，
There are pressure sensors all over
its head and body which can detect
周边任何东西的移动都能感应到。
anything moving
in the surrounding water.
它是午夜魔界中最贪婪的鱼。
It's the Midnight Zone's
most voracious fish.
但猎物会使用光线来干扰。
But prey use light as a distraction.
喷出些磷光油墨。
A decoy of luminous ink.
在这个漆黑一片的深深处，
Down here, in this blackness...
生物的生存突破了时光限制。
creatures live beyond
the normal rules of time.
管水母简直就是长生不老。
Siphonophores are virtually eternal.
它们不停地生长……
They repeatedly clone themselves...
有些长到甚至比一头蓝鲸还要长。
some eventually growing longer
than a blue whale.
这下面，竟然会“飘雪”。
Down here it snows.
断断续续的有机体碎片团
Continuous clouds of organic debris
从上方慢慢地飘落。
drift slowly down from above.
这些都是食物，滤食类动物
This is food, and a whole variety
全靠此生存。
of filter feeders depend on it.
包括水母……
Jellyfish...
和翩跹的海参。
and delicate sea cucumbers.
有1%的海中飘雪未被滤食
The 1% of marine snow they miss
最终沉到海底。
eventually settles on the sea floor.
经过数百万年后，形成了淤泥，
Over millions of years
it forms a layer of mud
厚达1英里。
up to a mile thick.
构成了一个空旷的平原，
It's an empty plain that covers
覆盖着地球表面的一半。
half the surface of our planet.
深海海床一开始似乎没有生物……
The deep sea bed
may at first appear lifeless...
但这里造就了一种奇特的淤泥生物。
but it's home to
a unique cast of mud-dwellers.
单棘躄鱼（海蟾蜍）
The sea toad.
这是伏击型捕猎者，长着大大的口
It is an ambush predator
with an enormous mouth...
有无限的耐性。
and infinite patience.
这种鱼已长期生活于此，
This fish has been living
for so long here
它的鳍已进化成
that its fins have changed
更好用的器官——
into something more useful.
就是脚。
Feet.
让它可以穿行于海床。
They help it shuffle about
on the sea floor.
烙饼章鱼（超萌的样子哦）
The flapjack octopus.
它徘徊于泥浆上面，细心查找，
It hovers just above the surface of
the mud as it delicately sifts
探寻蠕虫。
through it, searching for worms.
有一丁点风吹草动，
它就喷射而离，逃之夭夭。
But it can jet away at
the first sign of danger.
灰六鳃鲨，其体形如大白鲨。
A sixgill shark
as big as a great white.
它可能一整年都未进食了。
It may not have eaten
for an entire year.
它在淤泥平原上巡弋，
It patrols the mud plains
用的是它那最省体能的泳姿。
using a minimum amount of energy.
高高的上方，一只巨型抹香鲸的遗体
High above, the carcass of a huge
正在缓缓地腐化。
sperm whale is slowly decaying.
对于深海生物来说，
这是天上掉下来的大馅饼。
This will be a bonanza for the
creatures of the deep.
这是足足有30吨的食物啊。
Food, 30 tonnes of it.
终于，遗体沉降到海床了……
Finally, it settles
on the ocean floor...
而它的现身被迅速察觉。
and its presence is soon detected.
灰六鳃鲨的嗅觉极为敏锐。
Sixgill sharks have an
exceptionally acute sense of smell.
遗体现身后，只需25分钟……
Just 25 minutes after the whale's
carcass arrives...
灰六鳃鲨就发现了它。
a sixgill finds it.
每咬一口，鲜血横流。
Each bite releases blood
into the current.
有食物的消息迅速传开。
The news that food is here
spreads quickly.
另外两条如饥似渴的灰六鳃鲨赶到。
Two more ravenous sixgills arrive.
12小时内
Within 12 hours,
七条穷凶极恶的大鲨鱼，
there are seven enormous sharks
你争我抢，大快朵颐。
jostling with one another as they
compete to tear off mouthfuls.
每一条都争先恐后，毫不退让。
No-one is prepared to back off.
再过24小时，遗体的三分之一已被吃掉。
24 hours later and a third of the
carcass has gone.
最早来到的，已吃撑了。
The first arrival has gorged until
it's completely full.
下一顿，也许要等来年。
This single meal may be enough to
sustain it for a whole year.
这时候，收拾残局的部队现身了。
Now the clean-up team arrives.
蜘蛛蟹的后腿带有珊瑚，
Spider crabs carrying coral
in their hind legs,
大概是身体的临时盔甲。
presumably as makeshift body armour.
还有石蟹。
There are rock crabs here, too.
也许它们与鲨鱼同时发现遗体的……
They probably detected the carcass
almost as soon as the sharks...
只是跑得比较慢。
but they can't move as fast.
此后一个月，有30多种
A month on, and over 30 species of
腐食动物去消化掉
scavenger are clearing away the last
残存的遗体碎片。
edible fragments.
而这时候，腐食动物们迎来了它们的捕食者。
But now the scavengers are
attracting their own predators.
叉尾带鱼,这种鱼通常只会纵向游动，
Scabbardfish,
habitually swimming upright,
正在逐一捕食。
are picking them off one by one.
鲸鱼的骷髅开始散架了，
Some of the whale's teeth have been
dislodged as the skeleton starts to
而有的牙齿早已脱落。
fall apart.
四个月后，只剩下骸骨一堆。
Four months later, there is nothing
left but a few bones.
而对于某些生物来说……
But even they are food...
这也是食物。
for something.
僵尸蠕虫
Zombie worms.
它们能分泌酸液，然后钻入尸骨……
They tunnel into the bones by
injecting acid...
从而享用残存的微量骨髓。
and so reach the tiny amounts of
fat that still remain there.
It may take decades, but eventually
最终，大约数十年后，
这堆残留的骸骨也将碎成粉末，
the last of the bones will crumble
而整个30吨的遗体，
and the whole 30-tonne carcass
也终于完成了生态循环。
will have been recycled.
这沉底的鲸鱼遗体，有如海床沙漠里
A whale fall is a temporary oasis
短期呈现的绿洲。
in the desert of the sea floor.
而这里，还有永久的绿洲。
But there are permanent
oases here, too.
泥浆层突出的石块，
Rocks projecting above the mud
为深海珊瑚提供了栖身之地。
provide anchorage
for deep-sea corals.
往下深潜3.5英里（约5600米），
As far down as 3.5 miles,
在此深处，珊瑚品种繁多，
there are more species of coral
in the deep
比浅海处的热带珊瑚礁还多。
than on shallow tropical reefs.
没有阳光，
Without sunlight,
它们仅靠水流中的飘浮物维持生命。
they rely solely
on food drifting in the current.
它们一年只长宽
一条头发丝这么点。
And they grow just
a hair's breadth a year.
而有些珊瑚寿命长达4000年。
But some of them can live
for 4,000 years.
就如浅海珊瑚一样，
They, like their shallow water
relatives,
这里的珊瑚为所有其他生物提供了家园。
provide homes for
all kinds of other creatures.
珊瑚中，生长着一种极为美丽的海绵动物。
Growing among the corals is one of
the most beautiful of sponges.
这叫维纳斯花篮。
This is Venus' flower basket.
海绵动物内有寄居客。
These sponges have lodgers.
磷虾
Shrimps.
珊瑚礁里有大量捕食者，
There are plenty of predators
on the reef,
所以磷虾算得上幸福了。
so the shrimps are fortunate.
这一雌一雄，自幼就钻进海绵内了，
Both this male and female were swept
into this sponge
when they were tiny larvae,
伴同海绵所食用的
along with the minute particles of
微细颗粒一起。
food on which the sponge feeds.
它们青梅竹马，长相厮守。
They found each other and have been
here ever since.
现已发育成熟，
Now they're full-grown
雌虾准备产卵。
and the female is carrying eggs.
幼虾孵化后，将游出海绵。
Once hatched, the larvae will swim
out through the sponge's walls.
而成虾则在此终其一生。
But the shrimps will never leave.
它们出不去啊。
They can't.
小时候进得来，但现在体形太大了，
They are now far too big to go out
the way they came in,
而且毫无疑问
它们肯定更愿意长留于此，
and no doubt they will live longer
here than they would
因为如果在外四处浪荡的话，
一点也不保险。
if they were wandering about on the
reef unprotected.
然而，海绵这种最为低等的动物，
But how one of the simplest of all
animals, a sponge,
是如何构建如此复杂的结构，
is able to build
such a complex structure,
去为磷虾提供庇护呢？
to the great benefit of the
shrimps...
这真是个谜……
is a mystery...
神乎其神。
and surely a marvel.
但是，如今，它们的恒久乐土
却面临着土崩瓦解。
But today their timeless world is
being reduced to rubble.
因为过渡打渔，上层海域生物锐减，
As overfishing empties the
surface waters of the seas,
拖网渔船则对深海赶尽杀绝。
trawlers have started
to ransack the deep.
不计其数的珊瑚礁，
Now countless numbers of the reefs
那些数千年以来一直
欣欣向荣的珊瑚礁
that have flourished here
for millennia
如今，沦为死灰。
lie in ruins.
时光流逝，海床上的有机质缓慢腐化……
Over time, organic matter on the sea
floor slowly decays...
产生出沼气。
producing methane.
在墨西哥湾
In the Gulf of Mexico
火山喷释放出超级咸的液体。
these eruptions also release
a super-salty liquid.
卤水
Brine.
其密度比海水高五倍，
Five times heavier than seawater,
它们在海床上大量积淀。
it accumulates in great pools
on the sea floor.
此情此景，难以明述。
It's difficult to make sense
of the sight.
一个15米深的浓缩盐液湖，
A lake of concentrated saltwater,
15 metres deep
就位于海床上。
at the bottom of the sea.
更为神奇的是，在其周边
Around its margin,
perhaps even more strangely,
竟然物种繁多。
there is a profusion of life.
巨蚌，寿命可长达百岁甚至更多，
Giant mussels, that can live and
grow for a century or more,
紧紧地凑在一起，
pack tightly together,
以蚌为食的虾蟹，则相形见绌。
dwarfing the shrimps and squat
lobsters that feed around them.
连鳃鳗、腐食动物等
Cutthroat eels, scavengers,
来到卤水湖边觅食。
come to the shores of the brine lake
in search of something edible.
有的甚至冒险游进卤水。
Some even venture into the brine.
在里面呆久了，
Spending too long in it
能使连鳃鳗中毒性休克。
can send an eel into toxic shock.
求生的唯一指望，就是游出去。
Its only hope is to rise above it.
它挣扎着，成功逃命了。
It manages to escape.
有些就没这么走运。
Others are not so lucky.
卤水能让尸体防腐……
The brine embalms their bodies...
数十年来，罹难的生物
and the casualties of decades
在周边堆积。
accumulate around the margins.
但在深海，有些地方更为凶险。
But parts of the deep are
even more hostile.
好几处地方，巨大的裂缝蜿蜒数英里，
In places, gigantic cracks stretch
for many miles
贯穿着海床……
across the ocean floor...
形成了直探地核的峡谷。
canyons that plunge towards the
centre of the Earth.
通过探测船的扫描，可以画出
Scans from survey vessels make it
possible to graphically reconstruct
这片浩瀚海洋的地貌图谱。
an image of this
vast submarine landscape.
其最深之处，差不多有七英里
（约11公里）
The deepest of all,
at almost seven miles,
那是太平洋的马里亚纳海沟
is the Mariana Trench
in the Pacific Ocean.
连珠穆朗玛峰也比不过它。
Even Mount Everest
could disappear inside it.
这些深深的沟壑里，
Down here, in these deep ravines,
一度被认为，生命无论如何已不复存在。
it was once thought that nothing
whatever could possibly survive.
而事实上，竟然是有……
But there is life even here...
一种海蜗牛。
a kind of sea slug.
被称为“海猪”
A so-called "sea pig".
它们，以及另外一些低等生物，在此生存，
They, and other simple creatures,
manage to survive on the
所依靠的，
是极其微量飘落此处的食物。
minuscule amount of food
that drifts down here.
这种海星，
Like this starfish,
能承受50架大型喷气式客机的重压。
they can withstand pressure
equivalent of 50 jumbo jets
stacked on top of one another.
远程摄像机揭示了
A remote camera probe reveals
一个最为惊人的发现。
the most extraordinary
discovery of all...
飘逸的狮子鱼。
the ethereal snailfish.
这里足有五英里深，
At five miles down,
这是目前发现的生长在最深海域的鱼。
this is the deepest living fish
so far discovered.
难以想象，
No-one imagined that an animal as
象鱼这样的高等生物
complex as a fish could exist
竟能在如此巨大的水压下存活。
in such extreme pressures.
从海底最深处，到阴阳魔界的上限，
From the greatest depths to the
uppermost limit of
似乎没有一处，
the Twilight Zone, it seems that
there is nowhere in the deep sea
是生命无法触及的。
where life of some kind
can't survive.
如今我们认为：深海，也许正是
And we now think that the deep sea
may well be
地球生命的起源之处。
where life on Earth began.
这里，潜藏着
Here, in a world hidden within
地球上最为壮观的地貌……
the greatest geological
feature on Earth...
就在各大洋的中心地带，
running right down the middle of
the world's oceans,
存在着环绕全球的海底山脉。
an underwater mountain range,
spanning the entire globe.
这叫大洋中脊(又称中央海岭）
The Mid-Ocean Ridge.
在南太平洋，
In the South Pacific,
海床被大洋中脊所分裂。
the ocean floor is being torn apart.
超过四分之三的地球火山活动
Over three quarters of the planet's
volcanic activity
发生于深海……
occurs in the deep...
其中绝大部分都沿着大洋中脊分布。
almost all of it along the
Mid-Ocean Ridge.
然而，如此剧烈的火山喷发
却造就了物种的多样性。
But from this titanic violence
come great riches.
天然气和滚烫的水从裂缝喷涌而出。
Gases and scalding water gush up
through the crevices.
喷流中冷凝出来的矿物质形成巨大的烟囱……
Minerals condensing from these jets
build up great chimneys...
也就是火山口。
hydrothermal vents.
这个火山口足有30米高，
This one, 30 metres tall,
取名为“哥斯拉”。
has been named Godzilla.
相当惊人的是，目前我们发现
Astonishingly, we now know
其物种的丰富程度，
that they hold as much life
堪比热带雨林。
as tropical rainforests.
某些地方，五十万只动物
In places, half a million
individual animals
聚居在一平方米的面积内。
are crammed into
a single square metre.
它们全靠细菌维持生命。
They depend entirely for
their food on bacteria.
他们以溶解在灸热流体中的化学物质为食。
And THEY feed on chemicals dissolved
in the searingly hot fluid.
蟹所食用的，是覆盖在蟹壳上的细菌层。
Crabs consume the bacterial mats
that coat their shells.
有的生物则在其体内
Others maintain bacterial cultures
培养细菌。
actually within their bodies.
磷虾就在其口腔培养细菌，
Shrimps carry such cultures
in their mouthparts,
但这种策略满带危险。
but that is a strategy
fraught with danger.
因为，要给那些微生物提供营养，
To provide sustenance
for these microbes
磷虾必须冲入炽热的火山口……
the shrimps must dash
into the hot vents...
一不留神，就变成白灼虾咯。
and that risks being boiled alive.
过去十年，
In the last decade
被发现的火山口数量倍增。
the number of hydrothermal vents
discovered has doubled.
每一个都有其独特的物理性质和生物群落。
Every one has its own unique
character and community.
而其中，也许最为重要的一个，
就位于大西洋。
But perhaps the most important one
of all is in the Atlantic.
它被称为“失落之城”。
It has been named "The Lost City".
火山口高达60米，
Within its 60-metre towers,
这里面，奇幻迷离。
something truly extraordinary
is taking place.
在极高的水压和水温下，烃化物——
Under extremes of pressure and
temperature, hydrocarbons -
这种构成所有生物最基本成分的分子——
the molecules that are the basic
component of all living things -
就这么自然而然地合成了。
are being created spontaneously.
事实上，目前许多科学家认为
Indeed, many scientists now believe
地球上的生命正是这么起源的，
that life on Earth may have begun
就在这么样的火山口上，
around a vent like this,
远在40亿年之前。
four billion years ago.
据我们所知，木星和土星的卫星上
We now know that there are deep seas
就存在着深海。
on the moons of Jupiter and Saturn.
既然这里的极端环境下
If life can exist under such
可以存在生物，
extreme conditions down here,
那么理所当然地，那里也很可能
then surely it could exist
存有生命。
somewhere out there.
摄制组花了上千小时拍摄深海，
The team spent more than 1,000 hours
filming in the deep ocean,
拍摄工具主要就是“阿露雪”号研究船
mostly from the research vessel
Alucia and her twin submersibles,
以及“深漫”号和“耐抵”号这两部潜水神器。
Deep Rover and Nadir.
它们的最大任务就是去南极洲，
Their most ambitious mission
was to Antarctica,
下沉三分之二英里，去拍摄生命，
hoping to film life
two thirds of a mile down,
这是前所未有的探索。
something never attempted before.
老实说，能否有所收获，我们心里没底。
We honestly do not know what we're
going to find down there.
这是个人类从未探索过的地方。
We're going to a place that has
never been explored.
可能一无所获，可能大获丰收，
There could be nothing,
there could be a carpet of life,
也可能间乎两者之间。无从预知。
there could be anything in between.
Who knows?
技术挑战极大。
It's a huge technical challenge.
水温低至零下1.8摄氏度。
The water temperature here can reach
minus 1.8 Centigrade.
如此极端的环境之下，
No-one knows for sure
how the subs will cope
潜水器能否应付得来？没人敢打包票。
with this extreme environment.
好啦，好啦。我来把它清掉。
OK. Right, I'm going to soak it up.
OK.
首次下潜的半小时后，
Just half an hour into the very
first dive,
潜水器舱底出现了一滩水。
a puddle is forming
on the floor of the sub.
奥娜确认这是海水。
Orla confirms it's seawater.
是的，收到。我来把这滩水清除掉吧，
Yeah, Roger. I'm just try to soak up
this puddle of water,
然后再看看还会不会漏水。
and then see if any more comes.
他们必须找到漏点，并快速堵上。
They must find the leak
and repair it fast.
你想在我这上面敲……
Are you going to knock that over
my...? Yeah.
我们的小艇才下潜了450米，
而水渗进来了。
You're at 450 metres in a small
bubble and water's coming in.
升回水面需半小时。
That's a half an hour straight shot
back up to the surface.
心里想着：
You're kind of thinking about,
“水会全灌进来么？这可咋办啊！”
"Are we going to fill up with water?
And if we are, there's no way out!"
是的
Yeah.
船员们训练有素，早有应急预案。
The sub pilots are well drilled for
emergencies.
——递过来吧。   ——好的
Just pass them over. Yeah.
劳夫迅速找到了漏水点并进行修补。
Ralph quickly finds the flood
and fixes it.
他从容自若，
He made it all seem absolutely
ordinary and normal and,
“我可是训练有素，你别担心，”
"I've got this covered,
don't you worry,"
20分钟后，他搞掂了。
and within 20 minutes, he did.
南极洲南部水域也许很富饶，
The waters of the Antarctic Sound
are potentially rich
但也变幻莫测。
but also treacherous.
海峡内地势险恶，有“冰山胡同”之称。
The Sound is ominously known as
"Iceberg Alley".
我们得找个潜水器能安全升降的地方，
We've got to find a place where we
can get the submarines down and up
避免冰山把它们撞翻。
safely without any icebergs coming
along and bowling them over.
这感觉有点象玩"太空侵略者"游戏。
I've got a feeling it's going to be
a bit like a game of Space Invaders.
一立方米的水就重达一吨。
A metre cube of ice weighs a tonne.
你开始在球形舱体上打磨，它相当精美。
You start sort of grinding that
around the sphere, it's delicate.
就象一个巨大的复活节彩蛋。
It's like a big Faberge egg.
有次下潜，他们正好来到了冰山的下面。
One dive brings them right up to the
underside face of an iceberg.
上方都是冰山，有的象小汽车这么大，
There are icebergs up there that are
the size of a small car, and
有的则大如伦敦海德公园（足有360多英亩）
then there are icebergs up there
that are the size of Hyde Park.
超级大。
Enormous.
环境瞬息万变。
Conditions here
can change in an instant.
船长呼叫着下方的潜艇。
The captain radios down to the subs.
我担心冰块会砸到你们。我就怕这个。
.
好的，收到。
Yeah, Roger that.
这里有好几个冰山正在沿着海峡下沉，
We've currently got a couple of big
icebergs coming down
看样子它们将要相撞。
the channel, and it looks like
they're on a collision course.
上方冰山的碰撞声能听得一清二楚。
The impact of two icebergs colliding
overhead is clearly heard.
那是冰块。
That is ice.
冰山相撞的同时，天气急剧恶化，
With icebergs colliding above and
the weather turning fast,
潜艇被迅速召回。
the subs are quickly recalled.
又一次，徒劳而返。
Once again
their efforts are thwarted.
终于，两周后，环境有所改善。
Finally, after two weeks,
conditions are just right.
又来一次，队员们挑战冰山胡同里
1000米的深潜。
Once again the team attempt their
1,000-metre dive in Iceberg Alley.
下潜了一个小时后，他们接近目标了。
An hour after leaving the surface
they close in on their goal.
999米。
999.
指挥官，指挥官。
Control, control.
我是“耐抵”号
This is Nadir
我们正在深潜，深度—— 1000米。
on bottom, depth -
one-zero-zero-zero metres.
收到。 深度 —— 1000米。
Roger. Depth - 1,000 metres.
指挥完毕。创造新纪录了！
Control out. New record!
人工驾驶的潜艇，
首次在南极洲下潜至1000米！
First manned sub dive
to 1,000 metres in Antarctica!
在海床上，这个世界的尽头，
At the bottom of the ocean, at the
end of the world,
所发现的物种数量，令人目瞪口呆。
the amount of life they find is
astonishing.
同样令人目瞪口呆的是，
But they are equally astonished
to find that,
海平面下的三分之二英里处，
two thirds of a mile from the
surface,
冰山依旧危机四伏。
icebergs are still a danger.
冰山融化过程中，可能有石块坠落，
Rocks can drop from them
as they melt,
这一块，正好坠于潜艇前方。
and one lands
right in front of the sub.
大部分开着潜艇的人，都不曾想到，
I don't think many people who are
diving subs
还会有被大块落石坠击这等怪事。
ever consider big lumps of rock
landing on them.
这，这是非一般的风险。
It's, it's not your normal risk.
如果石块击中船身，
If it had hit the sphere,
很有可能产生划痕。
there's a good chance it would have
put a nice scratch down it.
如果被10，15甚或20吨的重物击中的话，
If something of ten, 15, 20 tonnes
had hit the sub,
潜艇就成为废铁了。
it would completely destroy it.
但其后的数次下潜，
But over the following dives
令队员们意识到，
正是这些坠落的石块，
the team learns it's these
very drop stones
使南极洲深海变得富饶，
that enrich the Antarctic
deep sea bed,
因为它们为生命的欣欣繁衍，
提供安居之所。
creating firm anchor points
for life to thrive.
看来，要想对深海生物的
复杂性和多样性心领神会，
Proof that the only way to fully
appreciate the complexity and
唯一办法，就是亲自下来走一趟。
abundance of life in the deep
is to go there ourselves.
下一集，我们将进入繁华的珊瑚礁。
Next time, we travel to bustling
coral reefs.
这里，动物们必须使出浑身解数，
Here, animals must go to
extraordinary lengths
以求在拥挤城市那成存败亡的
竞择游戏中，占得先机……
to get ahead of the competition in
these crowded cities.